Guide to the Rice University Provost's Office Records: William E. Gordon, 1980-1985 UA 091
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Provost's Office Records: William E. Gordon
1980-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gordon, William E.
UA 091
11.25 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
These records reflect the daily business of the Provost's office under physicist and astronomer William E. Gordon's leadership (1980-85). They reveal the daily business of the Provost's Office, which has the overall responsibility for the institution's educational and research programs.
Biographical Note
William E. Gordon's appointment as provost and vice president of Rice University began July 1, 1980. He retired July 1, 1985, although he continued to serve as provost until his replacement reported to work in spring 1986.
Gordon came to Rice from Cornell University in 1966 and taught space physics and astronomy, as well as electrical engineering, during his 19 years on the Rice faculty. Prior to his becoming provost and vice president in 1980, he served as dean of natural sciences (1975-80) and dean of science and engineering (1966-75).
He attained international prominence through his work on the Arecibo Ionospheric Observatory in Puerto Rico, a project he conceived, planned and directed during the first years after its completion, 1960-65. It is the world's largest radar-radio-telescope, sometimes described as earth's ear turned to outer space.
Recipient of numerous honors and awards, Dr. Gordon had the rare distinction of being a member of both the National Academy of Sciences and National Academy of Engineering. He was a fellow of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers and the American Geophysical Union, and past president of the International Union of Radio Science (1981-84).
Excerpted from press release of Rice University Information Services 2/22/1985; 4/2/1980.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 15 boxes of records from the provost's office during Dr. Gordon's tenure (1980-85).
Series I contains the On Campus-General files. They contain correspondence and documents pertaining to the non-academic departments of the university. The material includes budget information, computer/computing at Rice, including ICSA files, Fondren Library correspondence, promotion and teaching evaluations, space allocations and other files on non-academic departments such as Rice University Studies, Jefferson Davis and various other office files.
Series II contains the On Campus Academic files. They contain correspondence and documents that passed between the provost and the university academic departments.
Access Restrictions
Permission to access these records must be obtained from the Provost's Office. Form to request permission may be obtained from the Woodson Research Center.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
The Provost Records for Dr. William E. Gordon are divided into two series, each with folders arranged alphabetically by name and then chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I: On Campus – General, 1980-85. (Boxes 1-9A)
Series II: On Campus – Academic Units, 1980-85. (Boxes 10-13)
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Provost's Office 8/1989, 6/1990, 8/1990, and 7/1995.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Education
Subjects (Persons)
Gordon, William E.; Gordon, William E.
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Office of the Provost
- Series I: On Campus - General, 1980-85
  - AAUP, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Advising, 1984-85 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Affairs Committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Deans, 1980-81,1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - (VP) Administration, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Admissions Office, 1980-85, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Association, 1981, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Committee on Athletics, 1980, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Institute, 1980-83, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Apple Consortium, 1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - (Rice)-Baylor College of Medicine-HISD, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Budget/s, 1980/81 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Budget/s, 1981/82 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Budget/s, 1982/83 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Budget/s, 1983/84 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Budget/s, 1984/85 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Budget/s, 1985/86 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Budget/s, 1986/87 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Budget requests for computing equipment and services, 1984-85 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Campus Business Office, 1980-85 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chairs, 1980-83, 1984-85 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Class/Conference Rooms, 1980, 1982-83, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - College Courses, 1981, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Colloquia, Student Assistants, Symposia, etc., 1980-84 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Computer Advisory Board, 1983-84 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Computer Aided Design (CAD) proposal, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Computer Committee, 1980-84 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Computer Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Computer Committee minutes and agendas, 1980-85 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Computer Subcommittee on Personal Computers, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Computing Board, 1983-85 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Computervision, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Continuing Studies, 1980-85 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cost centers, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - DAAD, 1982-84 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dean of Advanced Studies and Research, 1980-85 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dean of Architecture, O. Jack Mitchell, 1985 (Box 2A, Folder 1)
  - Dean of Engineering, 1980-85 (Box 2A, Folder 2)
  - Accreditation Board for Engineering Technology (ABET) Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume I/William Marsh Rice University (Box 2A, Folder 3)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Chemical Engineering (Box 2A, Folder 4)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Civil Engineering (Box 2A, Folder 5)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Electrical Engineering (Box 2A, Folder 6)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Materials Science (Box 2A, Folder 7)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Mechanical Engineering (Box 2A, Folder 8)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Volume II/Mechanical Engineering, June 1984 (Box 2A, Folder 9)
  - ABET Questionnaire, May 1981 - Visitations, 1981, 1984 (Box 2A, Folder 10)
  - Dean of Humanities, Allen Matusow, 1980-85 (Box 2A, Folder 11)
  - Dean of Natural Sciences, G. K. Walters, 1980-85 (Box 2A, Folder 12)
  - Dean of Social Sciences, Joseph Cooper, 1980-85 (Box 2A, Folder 13)
  - Dean of Students, 1983-84 (Box 2A, Folder 14)
  - Dean's meetings, 1980-81 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dean's meetings, 1982-85 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Departmental chairmen memos, 1980-83 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Facilities budget requests, 1981/82 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Facilities budget requests, 1983/84 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Facilities budget requests, 1984/85 - 85/86 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Faculty annual reports, 1982/83 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Appointments, 1981/83 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Faculty statistics, 1980/81 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fondren Library, 1980/81 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fondren Library, 1981/82 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fondren Library, 1982/83 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fondren Library, 1983/84 (folder 1) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fondren Library, 1983/84 (folder 2) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fondren Library, 1984/85 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Fondren Library/Friends (FOF), 1980, 1983-85 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fondren Library/HARLIC/ARL, 1980, 1982-83 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fondren Library/Houston Academy of Medicine, Medical Center Library, 1982-84 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fondren Library/Huxley Celebration, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fondren Library/Johnson Space Center, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fondren Library/new courses or programs, 1981, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fondren Library/Patent Depository, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Fondren Library/permission to recruit, 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Fondren Library/retrospective conversion, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Huxley Symposium, NEH Proposal, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - ICSA general, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - ICSA general, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - ICSA general, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - ICSA general, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - ICSA general, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - ICSA general, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - ICSA allocations, administrative, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - ICSA allocations, administrative, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - ICSA allocations, administrative, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - ICSA allocations, administrative, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - ICSA allocations, administrative, 1984-85 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - ICSA allocations, computers, 1982/83 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - ICSA allocations, computers, 1983/84 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - ICSA allocations, computers, 1984/85 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - ICSA allocations, educational, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - ICSA allocations, research, 1980-85 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - ICSA Annual Report, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - ICSA Annual Report, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - ICSA budget, 1983, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - ICSA charges/rate change, 1980, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - ICSA Computer Science, 1980, 1984 (folder was unlabeled) (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - ICSA computing upgrade, general, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - ICSA computing upgrade, general, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - ICSA computing upgrade, proposal, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - ICSA contracts (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - ICSA Educom, 1980-84 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - ICSA Educom Seminar, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - ICSA Edunet, 1980-84 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - ICSA equipment, 1981-82, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - ICSA Horace Flatt, 1981-82 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - ICSA, IBM, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - ICSA memberships, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - ICSA miscellaneous, 1980-82 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - ICSA Mudd Building/ad hoc committee on academic use, 1980-83 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - ICSA Night Owls timesharing, 1980-81, 1984-85 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - ICSA operations, 1980-82, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - ICSA Period 3 research accounts, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - ICSA revenues, 1980-85 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - ICSA Self-Study Panel on computing, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - ICSA student research, 1981-82 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - (ad hoc committee) Industrial Sponsors for Rice Research, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Jefferson Davis, 1980-83 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory enhancement, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Languages, 1981-83 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Pending, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal, 1980-81, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - President/3 VP's, 1980-81 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Preregistration, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - PRIME, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Promotions, 1981/82 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Promotions, 1982/83 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Promotions, 1983/84 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Promotions, 1984/85-86 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Publications Revolving Fund, 1980-85 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Registrar, 1980-85 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Registrar's report, 1980-84 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Rice Architecture Computer Lab (RACL), 1983 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Rice Institute for Policy Analysis (RIPA), 1984-85 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Rice University Fund, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Rice University Historical Society, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Rice University Studies, 1980-85 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - ROTC, 1981-82, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Safety Officers, 1981-81, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Salary Report, 1980-81 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - SASS, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scienta, 1980-85 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Background (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Budgets (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Charges for panels 1-9 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Final Report Schedule (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - The Goals Manual, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Hudspeth Survey (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Library Material (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Master Information (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Master Plan for Growth, Cesar Pelli and Associates, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Preliminary Panels Report (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Steering Committee and Panels Directory (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS)/Brochures, Manuals, Guidelines and Other College Studies (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Commission on Colleges, Report of the Visiting Committee, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Correspondence, 1980, 1982-85 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Draft Approvals, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Follow Up, 1984-85 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Meeting, Atlanta, GA, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Meeting, New Orleans, LA, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1984 (Rice University) Self-Study Materials - SACS, Site Visit Correspondence, 1984-85 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Space, 1981/82 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Space, 1982/83 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Space, 1983/84 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Space, 1984/85 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Staff meetings, 1980-81 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Standing committees, 1981-83 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - (Academic) State of the University, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Summer program, 1980-85 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Teaching evaluations, Spring 1981 (Box 9A, Folder 1)
  - Teaching evaluations, Fall 1981 (Box 9A, Folder 2)
  - Teaching evaluations, Spring 1982 (Box 9A, Folder 3)
  - Teaching evaluations, Fall 1982 (Box 9A, Folder 4)
  - Teaching evaluations, Spring 1983 (Box 9A, Folder 5)
  - Teaching evaluations, Fall 1983 (Box 9A, Folder 6)
  - Teaching evaluations, Spring 1984 (Box 9A, Folder 7)
  - Teaching evaluations, Fall 1984 (Box 9A, Folder 8)
  - Teaching evaluations, Spring 1985 (Box 9A, Folder 9)
  - Teaching evaluations, Fall 1985 (Box 9A, Folder 10)
  - Teaching evaluations master file, 1980-85 (Box 9A, Folder 11)
  - Teaching evaluations personnel, 1980-85 (Box 9A, Folder 12)
  - Tuition rebates to cost center schools, 1983 (Box 9A, Folder 13)
  - University Council/Promo Committee, 1980/81 (Box 9A, Folder 14)
  - University research grants, 1982-83, 1985 (Box 9A, Folder 15)
- Series II: On Campus - Academic Units, 1980-85
  - Anthropology, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Architecture, 1980/81 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Architecture, 1981/82 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Architecture, 1982/83 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Architecture, 1983/84 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Architecture, 1984/85 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Art and Art History, 1981-82 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Chemical Engineering, 1980-81, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Chemistry, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Civil Engineering, 1981-82 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Computer Science, 1984-85 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Economics, 1981, 1983-84 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Education, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Electrical Engineering and Biomedical Engineering, 1980, 1982-83 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Engineering, 1980/81 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Engineering, 1981/82 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Engineering, 1982/83 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Engineering, 1983/84 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Engineering, 1984/85 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - (School of) Engineering Abercrombie Lab Project, 1981-82 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - (School of) Engineering Advisory Council, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - English, 1980-81, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - French and Italian, 1981-82 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Geology and Geophysics, 1980-81, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - German and Slavic Studies, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Health and Physical Education, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - History, 1981-83 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Humanities, 1980/81 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Humanities, 1981/82 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Humanities, 1982/83 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Humanities, 1983/84 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Humanities, 1984/85 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Jones School of Administration, 1980/81 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Jones School of Administration, 1981/82 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Jones School of Administration, 1982/83 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Jones School of Administration, 1983/84 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Jones School of Administration, 1984/85 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Jones School of Administration Dean Search Committee, 1980/81 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Linguistics and Semiotics, 1980, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Mathematical Sciences, 1983-84 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Mathematics, 1983-84 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science, 1983-84 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science Accreditation, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Military Science, 1980/81 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Military Science, 1981/82 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Military Science, 1982/83-1983/84 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Military Science, 1984/85 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Natural Sciences, 1980/81-1981/82 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Natural Sciences, 1982/83 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Natural Sciences, 1983/84 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Natural Sciences, 1984/85 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy, 1980-82, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Physics, 1980-82, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Political Science, 1980-81 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Psychology, 1980-81 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Religious Studies, 1980, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - ROTC credit for courses, 1980/81 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - ROTC credit for courses, 1983-84 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1980/81 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1981/82 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1982/83 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1983/84 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1984/85 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Shepherd School of Music Search Committee, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Social Sciences, 1980/81 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Social Sciences, 1981/82 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Social Sciences, 1982/83 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Social Sciences, 1983/84 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Social Sciences, 1984/85 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - (School of) Social Sciences Policy Center, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Sociology, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Spanish, Portuguese, Classics, 1983, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 14)